# **Margo Nowicka**

I am a new media artist, creative coder and animator. My current artistic and research interests reside in deconstructing the totalistic discourses of computation. I want to foster a more critical understanding of computer logic by devising softer, more intelligible modes of algorithmic representation.

I come from Wrocław, Poland and am currently based in Helsinki, Finland.

Artistic portfolio: margonowicka.com
Programming portfolio: github.com/nowickam
Contact: mngnowicka@gmail.com

## **Education**

## MA in New Media, Aalto University

2021-2023 | Espoo, Finland

Highest grade (5) for the MA thesis "Aurinko and Selene: Conceptual influences of computation in culture and science through the lens of Finnish genetic study": <a href="https://urn.fi/URN:NBN:fi:aalto-202312037039">https://urn.fi/URN:NBN:fi:aalto-202312037039</a>.

Student exchange in Information and Communication Technology, Kungliga Tekniska Högskolan 2019-2020 | Stockholm, Sweden

### **BSc in Computer Science, Warsaw University Of Technology**

2017-2021 | Warsaw, Poland

Summa cum laude with the BSc thesis "Audio-driven facial animation" implementing machine learning approach to algorithmically generate convincing facial animation for human speech.

Warsaw University of Technology Rector's scholarship for high academic performance for 2020/21.

# **Experience**

#### **Animation Director and Exhibition Designer**

2.2024-10.2024 | Helsinki Central Library Oodi, Helsinki, Finland

Department of Art and Media, Aalto University, Espoo, Finland

Graphic design and direction of the 2D short animation "Aurinko and Selene" as part of an exhibition at Helsinki Central Library Oodi on the collaboration between the Information Design focus group at Aalto University and Finngen genetic research project.

https://www.aalto.fi/en/events/lines-of-descent-data-visualisation-tools-to-empower-genetic-research https://oodihelsinki.fi/event/helsinki:agjavemcau/lines-of-descent/?lang=en https://infodesign.aalto.fi/collaboration/

#### Projection Designer in the "Rottien pyhimys" musical

2.2023-5.2023, 1.2024-2.2024, 9.2024-10.2024 | Musiikkiteatteri Kapsäkki, Helsinki, Finland Aleksanterin teatteri, Helsinki, Finland

Design of the stage projections for a musical directed by Reetta Ristimäki based on the novel by Anneli Kanto. TouchDesigner interactive projections and formal grammar visualisation.

https://www.gretatuotanto.fi/rottien-pyhimys

### Generative Video Designer in the "Ihmisen jälkeen / Posthuman" chamber opera

1.2023-3.2023 | Dance House Helsinki, Helsinki, Finland

Video production for an experimental chamber opera written and directed by Temu Mäki in collaboration with composer Max Savikangas. Generative and artificial life simulations, 3D animation.

https://www.teemumaki.com/theater-posthuman.html

#### Animation Director for "Takeoff" slam poetry performance

12.2022 – 9.2023 | Department of Art and Media, Aalto University, Espoo, Finland

Direction of a short animation visualizing a poem by Giovanni Baudonck using 3D, produced with procedural modeling. A part of the Urban Travel Machines project, co-funded by the Creative Europe Programme of the European Union.

Presented in the Prima Vista Literary Festival as an immersive slam poetry performance in the planetarium in Tartu, Estonia. Open Call Winner in new media urban festival Kinomural 2023, Wrocław, Poland.

Official Selection in:

ZEBRA Poetry Film Festival 2023, Berlin, Germany,

Tokyo International Short Film Festival, Tokyo, Japan,

New York Tri-State International Film Festival, New York, USA,

Les Instants Vidéo, Marseille, France.

https://utm.ap-arts.be/

#### **Lecturer and Teaching Assistant**

10.2022-12.2022 | Department of Art and Media, Aalto University, Espoo, Finland

Teaching of an introductory course on web development for visual communication Master's students and assistance in the teaching of a creative coding course.

#### Research Assistant in a science communication project

6.2022-8.2022 | Department of Art and Media, Aalto University, Espoo, Finland

Visualization of the human genome analysis data for a scrollytelling website as a part of the genetic research project FinnGen.

https://geneviz.aalto.fi/what-is-finngen

#### **Animation Director for "Dysmorphia"**

6.2022-9.2023 | Department of Art and Media, Aalto University, Espoo, Finland

Direction of a 3D short animation on the themes of self image and social anxiety.

Received the Department of Art and Media grant for traveling to the Fredrikstad Animation Festival 2022.

Presented in Spring Demo Day 2022, Aalto Media Lab

https://medialabdemoday.aalto.fi/2022-spring/dysmorphia/.

Official Selection in:

Fredrikstad Animation Festival 2022, Fredrikstad, Norway,

15th Annual Short Short Story Film Festival, Bethel CT, USA,

23. Animatricks International Animation Festival, Helsinki, Finland, 17th Anim!Arte - International Student Animation Festival of Brazil, Rio De Janeiro, Brazil, Kinomural 2023, Wrocław Poland.

### **Research Assistant in Natural Computation research group**

7.2020-9.2020, 7.2021-9.2021, 11.2021-5.2022 | Department of Computer Science, Aalto University, Espoo, Finland

Scientific visualization of the interactions between DNA strands utilizing algorithmic and graph-theoretic approach.

Poster presentation in the International Conference on Unconventional Computation and Natural Computation 2021, Espoo, Finland and the 29th International Conference on DNA Computing and Molecular Programming, Sendai, Japan.

Published in the International Conference on Unconventional Computation and Natural Computation 2024, Pohang, Korea.

https://link.springer.com/chapter/10.1007/978-3-031-63742-1\_14

## **Skills**

generative programming (Processing, p5js, GLSL, openFrameworks)
data visualization (D3.js, THREE.js)
web development (HTML, CSS, JavaScript, React)
audiovisual exhibition and performance (TouchDesigner, PureData, Python, C++, Premiere, Kinect)
3D animation (Blender, Maya)
2D animation (TVPaint)
electronics (Arduino, Bela)
programming (C, C++, C#, Python, Java, JavaScript)
graphic design (Photoshop, InDesign)

# Languages

Polish native English fluent German basic